Maximilian, Emperor of Mexico collection 1847-1967 (bulk 1853-1867)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
- Series IV: Articles, Ephemera, Photographs, and Broadsides, 1855-1967
  - Broadside (Puebla). January 21, 1861 (Box 3)
    Miguel Castulo de Alatriste, Constitutional Governor of the free and sovereign State of Puebla, informs the inhabitants that through the Secretary of State and the Government Office the following decree has been communicated to him. This decree is issued by Benito Juarez, provisional constitutional President of the United States of Mexico, and concerns the civil status of individuals. The first 17 articles set forth the general rules. The subsequent articles (18-24) deal with birth certificates; the next articles (25-35) deal with marriage certificates; the last articles deal with death certificates. Issued in the Palace of The Governor General, Veracruz, July 28, 1859. Published in Puebla, January 21, 1861.
  - Broadside (Mexico). September 21, 1862 (Box 3)
    Supplement of The Herald, giving important news of the day, including the expected arrival of French troop reinforcements and the blockage of Tampico.
  - Broadside (Mexico). January 22, 1863 (Box 3)
    The Triumph of the National Army over the French at the Bar of Tampico. Artillery, supplies, war ammunition and three ships are taken. We have just received the very important communication which we hasten to publish. The invaders have just committed a new act of barbarism which has characterized all their acts in the Republic. At the same time the National Army has won another glorious triumph which should be placed at the side of that of 5 of May. The future of the Republic is brilliant at this moment. The enemy is advancing on Puebla; but in addition to the heroic and enthusiastic garrison that is found there, today the army fromthe center, 8000 strong is on the move. To the triumph of Puebla have been added almost at the same time those of Tampico and those of Acapulco, from whence the French have had to retire also, their barbaric bombardment on an empty city being futile, as was the fire and destruction in Tampico...
    Tampico, January 22, 1863. Juan de la Garza - Minister of War and Navy. (Partial translation).
  - Broadside (Mexico). January, 1863 (Box 3)
    Very Important Campaign Notices. Enemy movements.
    Samples of French civilization that the invaders offer us:
    Transgressions committed by the French troops in Tehuacan.
    The outrages committed at Tehuacan offend us to the quick.
    Take up arms, Mexicans! The Minister of War and Navy receives reports from the commander at Tehuacan that the enemy forces have taken that town, and that the population has suffered considerable losses... The Official Bulletin of December 31 says that "we have letters from Quecholac saying that French troops are continually arriving at Palmar; they will probably form their base for operations there..."
    More campaign notices: According to notices received, it seems that the enemy has finally decided to move and some of the advance guards have reached Queholac. From telegraphic information yesterday it is known that at 9 a.m. General Carbajal reached Acatzingo...
    San Agustin del Palmar: It has become known that General Forey reached this point accompanied by the traitor Almonte who had a horrible fear of remaining alone in Orizava...
    Reports from Tampico, Cuernavaca, Chautla... by Florencio M. del Castillo. (Partial translation).
  - Broadside (Mexico). February 11, 1863 (Box 3)
    Decree of Benito Juarez, Constitutional President of the United States of Mexico, setting a tax of one per cent for the Federal Administration Budget for the current year. A statement of what is taxable under this decree is given.
  - Broadside (Mexico). March 22, 1863 (Box 3)
    Correspondents Comonfort and Rozas Landa report from Rio Prieto on the occupational of Santiago by the French army. Have not been damaged by batteries; perhaps some houses located between the forts at San Javier and Carmen prevented it... The combat has begun. The first blood is flowing now. God save the Republic and reward the bravery of our men...
    Comonfort reports from Cuautlancingo: The enemy is organizing two strong columns, entered into light combat with the riflemen of Nuevo Leon, one man from the regiment of Parras was killed. Inform the President; he will continue in the field...
    Blanco and Comonfort exchange information about the dead soldier, and the President's plans to take up a subscription to pay the debts of the soldier...
    From the Venta de San Antonio, Comonfort gives additional reports on the movements of the troops, the position of the enemy, etc.
  - Broadside (Toluca). March 19, 1863 (Box 3)
    War news, issued by Secretario Eleuterio Avila, telling of the advance of French forces to the outskirts of Mexico City.
  - Broadside (Mexico). May 18, 1863 (Box 3)
    Ponciano Arriaga, Governor of the Federal District, to the inhabitants, know ye:
    "That through the Minister of Foreign Relations and Government the following has been addressed to me: That the President of the Republic has seen fit to declare that from today the Federal District is in a state of rigorous siege, and that in consequence the Military Command takes charge of political affairs."
  - Broadside (Mexico). May 18, 1863 (Box 3)
    "That the President has ordered:
    1) That within 3 days from the date of this supreme resolution all the French subjects in the City of Mexico and in other parts of the Federal District shall leave by the road of Morelia or of Queretaro to a distance not less than 40 leagues from this Capital; there can be no exemption except in the case of those physically disabled.
    2) This very day the French who are in the City of Mexico must hand over to the Government of the Federal District all the arms they have in their possession. The Government will give them a receipt and will fix a sum for them. A fine will be imposed on those who retain their arms.
    3) The French referred to in this resolution can dispose of their property freely, with the exception of their arms."
  - Broadside (Mexico). May 19, 1863 (Box 3)
    Minister of War and Navy reviews the war situation and transfers the President's exhortations to the civilian governors and military commanders of the various states to aid in the defense of Mexico City against the French.
  - Broadside (Puebla). May 21, 1863 (Box 3)
    Decree of General Forey under the authority of the Regency for the confiscation of the private property of Mexican citizens opposed to the French intervention.
  - Broadside (Mexico). May 28, 1863 (Box 3)
    Order of General Juan J. de la Garza, dealing with the evacuation from Mexico City of all females under 16 and all over 60 years of age in preparation for defense of the City.
  - Broadside (Mexico). June 10, 1863 (Box 3)
    "The General of the Division (Forey), Senator, and Commander in Chief of the Expeditionary Forces in Mexico, to the inhabitants of the Capital, know ye:
    I do not want to take a moment of rest before having expressed all my gratitude for the brilliant welcome which you have today given to the valiant army that I have the honor to command. I do not have words adequate to express what my heart has experienced, but I have contracted today a sacred debt -- that of working tirelessly to give you what you most desire: peace, order, justice and true liberty. I am counting on all good Mexicans to help me in the fulfilling of this mission...
    When an edifice has been destroyed it can only be rebuilt little by little if it is to be really solid. Have patience, therefore, and with Divine Protection in which I place all my confidence we shall overcome the difficulties of the great work of regeneration.
  - Broadside (Mexico). July 13, 1863 (Box 3)
    Proclamation by General Forey, commanding the French intervention forces, to dissident Mexicans to join him in setting up a stable government in Mexico. (In both Spanish and French).
  - Broadside (Mexico). July 16, 1863 (Box 3)
    Manuel G. Aguirre, Political Prefect of Mexico to the inhabitants, know ye:
    "That it has been brought to the attention of this Office that some business houses and work shops are keeping open for business on Sundays and Holidays. This is an infraction of the laws. I have arranged that those disobeying the law will be punished. The ruling published July 9, 1853 is here given..."
  - Broadside (Mexico). April 10, 1864 (Box 3)
    Supplement of The Society people. Two news items from New York via Veracruz, telling of the official acceptance by Maximilian of the throne of Mexico at Miramar, his residence in Trieste, Austria on April 10, 1864.
  - Broadside (Mexico). May 19, 1864 (Box 3)
    Jose del Villar y Bocanegra, Political Prefect of the Department of Valle de Mexico to the inhabitants, know ye:
    That I have received the following communication... Imperial Palace, Mexico, 19 of May, 1864. The Regency of the Empire has deigned to arrange the solemn publication of the act sent from Miramar by the Mexican Commission charged with the offering of the votes of the Mexicans and the Crown to Maximilian.
    Proclamation detailing the ceremony at Miramar Palace near Trieste, April 10, 1864, when Maximilian was offered the crown, giving names of those in attendance and full text of Maximilian's acceptance. The same day he issued a decree naming Juan N. Almonte his Lieutenant General in the Empire during the time which must elapse until he, the Emperor, can reach the Mexican territory. The Regency ceases to function upon receipt of this decree, and General Almonte as Lieutenant of the Empire is in charge of the Government. Issued by the Political Prefect, Jose del Villar y Bocanegra. Sec. Gen., Alejandro Villasenor.
  - Broadside (Veracruz). May 28, 1864 (Box 3)
    The Political Prefect of el Valle de Mexico to the inhabitants, know ye:
    That His Majesty, the Emperor Maximilian, addressed to the Mexicans the proclamation that I have the honor to communicate to you:
    "Mexicans: You wanted me! Your noble nation by a spontaneous majority has designated me to watch over your destinies from today on. I yield with joy to your call. However painful it may have been for me to say goodbye forever to my native country and to my people, I did it persuaded that the Almighty had appointed me through you to the noble mission of devoting all my strength and all my heart to a people who, worn out by combats and disastrous struggles, sincerely desire peace and well-being, to a people who, having gloriously established their independence, wish to enjoy the fruits of civilization and true progress... Let us unite to attain a common objective. Let us forget the sombre past, let us bury party hatred, and the dawn of deserved peace and happiness will come again radiant to the New Empire."
  - Broadside (Mexico). June 6, 1864 (Box 3)
    Second Supplement to no. 352 of The Society. Details concerning the entry of their Imperial Majesties into Puebla. Celebration, acclamation, ceremonies, order of the group which is to accompany their Majesties from Guadalupe on the 12th.
  - Broadside (Chapultepec). September 16, 1866 (Box 3)
    Decree by Maximilian in regard to land. Detailed provisions for the granting of land to small villages which require it for the support of their populations. (In Spanish and an Indian language).
  - Broadside (Zacapoaxtla). September 26, 1866 (Box 3)
    Rafael J. Garcia, provisional Governor of the free and sovereign State of Puebla, informs the inhabitants that:
    considering that all the citizens of the State have the strict duty of contributing in whatever manner it is possible for them to the defense of the country and the re-establishment of the Republic, that while those who have not been favored with wealth, are fulfilling that duty by offering their blood and their life to attain the freedom of the country, it is just from every point of view that those who have means should contribute, in proportion to their importance, for the expenses required by war. But in order to prevent extortion and to carry out the plan equitably, Garcia issues the decree governing the amounts and manner in which the contributions shall be made...
  - Broadside (Monterey). December 2, 1866 (Box 3)
    Supplement to no. 31 of the official newspaper of Monterey. Contains report of the Governor and Military Commander, M. Escobedo, of the Nueva Leon in regard to the surrender of Matamoros to the forces of the Army of the North, December 1, 1866.
  - Broadside (Puebla). March 11, 1867 (Box 3)
    Supplement to no. 18 of the official paper of Puebla. News from the Interior:
    A respectable person from Mexico writes to another person in this city the following: "In my last letter I informed you of the movements of the Army under the personal command of the Emperor, as far as Queretaro, and of how the forces of Escobedo had avoided combat. Now I have little to add. The rebels continued their retreat toward San Luis por la Laja, San Miguel and San Felipe. At seven this evening in combat between Escobedo's troops and those of the Emperor, there was a complete triumph for the Imperial Army. Escobedo and Trevino and various chiefs and officials were taken..."
    The General in Chief of the 3rd Division to the inhabitants of Puebla:
    "Fellow Citizens: After vacillating a thousand times, the enemy has finally resolved to come against the City. You all know that a serious illness kept me in my bed. But the nearness of the enemy renewed my enthusiasm and brought nearer to my mind the duties that bind me to you and to the National Government. You now have me at the head of the worthy and honorable soldiers whom I chance to command, and I am ready to inflict an exemplary punishment on the enemy and to sustain the cause of order and of society. Compatriots, do not doubt: the enemy will have to repent of its mad intention. The god of battles is with us. Your fellow citizen and friend, Manuel Noriega."
    The General in Chief of the 3rd Division of Puebla to the troops under his command:
    "Soldiers: Today the enemy has decided to test our valor and loyalty. I am counting on the loyalty and valor of the people of Puebla who have never allowed this heroic city to be attacked with impunity..."
  - Broadside (Puebla). March 17, 1867 (Box 3)
    Mars, God of Wars. New Bulletin; Political, Military and Police Paper. v. 1, no. 4. Defeat of the Rebels in the Interior. Toluca:
    It is known that at a late date the rebel forces were making ready to leave that city for Morelia. Those who are close to Mexico have received orders to withdraw to Toluca in order to proceed also to Morelia. The Mexican Times said Sunday afternoon: "On considering the map of Mexico and noting the position of the forces, we see clearly that the liberal chiefs have formed plans very like those which General Grant formed in order to defeat General Lee and take Richmond. We can say that Queretaro is the Richmond of this campaign, and that Escobedo approaching with his forces is the General Grant, while Corona in place of Sherman is little by little cutting communication and intercepting the supplies of the Imperial Army of Queretaro. The most blind of men can see what the plan of the liberals is, but it will not succeed for two reasons. First, because the Emperor Maximilian is a skilled leader with military experience and he will not divide his numerous army, but will move on Escobedo or on Corona to defeat each on separately. We do not believe that the liberals are anxious to take a chance against the 20,000 well-disciplined soldiers of the Emperor, supported by 60 pieces of artillery."
    The Union said yesterday that a Don Martin Estrada, and another person whose name they do not recall, have turned with 500 well-armed men in favor of the Emperor. The same paper said that 100 armed men who belonged to the French Army and who were fighting in the ranks of Riva Palacio have abandoned that standard and have presented themselves to the Imperial Government.
    Additional news of Valle de Mexico, the Interior, Queretaro, Cuautitlan. Rumor of a battle at Queretaro.
  - Broadside (Puebla). March 20, 1867 (Box 3)
    "Viva the Emperor!" General D. Manuel Noriega, in command of Imperial Forces in Puebla, publishes a congratulatory and encouraging letter received from Teodosio Lares of the government in Mexico for his (Noriega's) gallant defense of Puebla.
  - Broadside (Puebla). March 31, 1867 (Box 3)
    Supplement to no. 18 of the official paper of Puebla. Report on the communication of General Leonardo Marquez that he is coming with a column of 8,000 men from the three armies and hopes that the garrison at Puebla will do everything possible to hold out until he arrives.
    Manuel Noriega, Brigadier General in charge of the 3rd Division of the Second Body of the Imperial Army, to the loyal inhabitants of the beautiful and unconquered Puebla: an expression of faith in the success of the Emperor, and that victory for religion, the Union and Independence of Mexico will be attained...
  - Broadside (Zaragoza, i.e. Puebla). April 2, 1867 (Box 3)
    Orders of General Juan Ramirez, political head of the capital and district of the puebla of Zaragoza, to the inhabitants:
    Within 24 hours from 5 p.m. all materials of war abandoned by the enemy shall be turned over to the political government. Arms, horses, equipment that is hidden shall be turned over to the same office. Objects that have been used by the enemy in the construction of their fortifications will be collected and placed in the public granary at the disposal of the Government Office so that they may be returned to the owners. Those who keep in their possession arms abandoned by the enemy will be fined from 25 to 200 pesos or will be sentenced to from 1 to 4 months in prison.
  - Broadside (Zaragosa, i.e. Puebla). April 2, 1867 (Box 3)
    Bulletin from the East, no. 26. The capture of Puebla... A great event which brings out clearly the invincible force of the Republican troops... What has just happened in Puebla foretells with all certainly what will happen in Mexico and Queretaro, if the rest of the traitor factions persist in prolonging the struggle. In the midst of the confusion attendant upon the attack on the town, the General in charge did not forget the laws of society, and further, to arouse the local authorities to the necessity for keeping order he has taken the most earnest care that the conduct of the army should match its proverbial discipline...
    Telegrams of congratulation to Diaz from Gamboa, Rincon, and Garcia.
    Telegram of congratulation to Benitez from General Baranda.
  - Broadside (Zaragoza, i.e. Puebla). April 5, 1867 (Box 3)
    Tribute to his "companions in arms" from Porfirio Diaz, General in charge of the Army of the East, for the heroism and success as conquerors of Puebla.
  - Broadside (Puebla). April 6, 1867 (Box 3)
    Rafael J. Garcia, provisional Governor of the free and sovereign state of Puebla, to the inhabitants:
    "Fellow citizens: Providence has given me the honor of being at the head of the state at this moment of the reconquest. My presence in this capital after the glorious deeds that have just been finished has a meaning so obvious that there is not much left for me to say about the transcendency of the latest happenings in our domestic politics. Today legal order in its fullest sense has come again for Puebla... We must join together to pay tribute to the Army of the East. The mission of the troops has ended favorably as far as Puebla is concerned. Our federal and domestic institutions are now in charge throughout the state..."
  - Broadside (Puebla). (2 copies). April 7, 1867 (Box 3)
    Rafael J Garcia decrees that the rights to practice law or to be a notary or business agent given by the tribunals established by the usurping government are null and void. Those who are included in the article must present their diplomas within eight days to the Secretary of Justice.
  - Broadside (Zaragoza, i.e. Puebla). April 8, 1867 (Box 3)
    Notice: The Governor orders that all those individuals who served the Empire in civil or military capacity or in any manner present themselves in this Capital to the Secretary of Government and Military within three days, and that those who are outside of the Capital report to the political leaders. If they do not do so, action will be taken against them in accordance with the law of the 25th of January, 1863.
    Jose Maria Bautista, Secretary of Government and Militia
  - Broadside (Zaragoza, i.e. Puebla). April 9, 1867 (Box 3)
    Rafael J. Garcia, interim Governor of State of Puebla, informs the inhabitants that, in compliance with the provisions in Article 18 of the law of Dec. 4, 1860, he offers the following ruling concerning the bells: the ringing in the Capital as well as in the Districts shall be only at dawn, at 12 noon, 3 in the afternoon, the angelus, at 8 in the evening, and the curfew which is customarily from 9 to 10. Further regulations are given concerning the time. Anyone breaking these rules will be punished by a fine from 5 to 50 pesos.
  - Broadside (Zaragoza, i.e. Puebla). April 24, 1867 (Box 3)
    Rafael J. Garcia informs the inhabitants that the President of the Republic, Benito Juarez, has issued the following decree:
    Article 1, women uncloistered by virtue of the decree issued February 26 past will enjoy all the rights that the laws of the country grant to women...
    There are 17 more articles treating the status of these women and what rights and privileges they are to be guaranteed. (Written in pen at the end: "Decree of the 25th of this month.").
  - Broadside (Guadalupe Hidalgo). April 26, 1867 (Box 3)
    The General in Chief of the Army and the Eastern Division (Porfirio Diaz) to the inhabitants, know ye:
    that the owners, renters, administrators of the lands over which pass the wires or where are placed the telegraph posts which General Headquarters uses to communicate its orders, are responsible for any damage committed to such lines with the object of interrupting communications. The responsible parties spoken of in the above article will be fined 20 pesos for every post torn out, the same amount for every meter of wire that is missing, and a like amount for each day that the communication is broken off.
  - Broadside (Puebla). April 29, 1867 (Box 3)
    Juan Nepomuceno Mendez, Brigadier General of the Republican Army, Governor and Military Commandant of the State of Puebla, tells the inhabitants, his fellow citizens, that the worthy Chief of the Army of the East has honored him by putting him in charge for the time being of the government and of the military command of Puebla. The situations here, as well as in the whole country, is so difficult that Mendez asks the full cooperation of the citizens in carrying on the work. The army that is fighting for the cause of the Republic is worthy of the full consideration of every one. The knowledge that the State has of his conduct in office, and the publicity that all his acts will have in the very transitory period of his administration excuses him from setting forth the program he proposes to follow, but this can be summed up in a few words -- "blind obedience to law and the absolute triumph of the Republican Chiefs."
  - Broadside (Zaragoza, i.e. Puebla). April 29, 1867 (Box 3)
    Rafael J. Garcia, to his fellow citizens: